i know what kind of leadership training
i wish i'd had uh in my early 20s
uh late 20s even early 30s and so to
kind of go back down that path and say
hey guys you know i've skimmed my knee
plenty of times trying to
find my way forward and now you know let
me do my part to help you
not shy away from your challenges or
even provide all the solutions but to
give you the resources uh so that you
can
be more confident in the solutions that
you come up with for yourself as you
deal with life's inevitable challenges
knowledge is power
[Music]
to kind of resent ourselves you know
what would what would make this the best
podcast ever for you
um i like that question that's a good
that's a good intro question um
i think just um
reachable for the for the average person
i like to kind of not to overly we don't
have to really stay into the weeds and
overly dumb things down but i like to
try to treat it as um
remembering that the listener could be
some someone young or someone who has
really never experienced um you know
leadership or conflict resolution before
or that maybe they're maybe they're new
to this whole way of thinking so
just basically like
keeping our beginner in mind let's say
that yeah that's perfect um just to
dovetail on that right all right are you
familiar with the hemingway app at all
or no
i don't think so so the hemingway app i
learned about recently from another
coach and so what happens is is that it
rates like the difficulty of your
writing and if it's overly technical
like it'll tell you like this is grade
six seven eight nine and it actually
like forces you to kind of like simplify
it down so that a sixth grader can
understand it it's it's pretty uh it's
pretty amazing you're like i can't
believe i went through all this training
just still like dumb down my language
but yeah yeah to lessen the the
complexity of the words that i'm using
yes so sometimes i'll even notice that i
will um
i don't know i don't know if maybe it's
because we'll be listening to someone
who's using a lot of big words or we're
listening to someone explaining it in a
certain way so we'll use it i'll listen
to myself back on podcasts and i'm like
well i could have delivered that exact
same sentence in
10 words less but i added all these
complicated words um but yeah no like of
course we can feel free to to expand and
go as intricate as we'd like but it's
always like to remember that the little
guy you know just in case curse of
knowledge man absolutely you're just
like oh because i mean we do that in
pharmacy school we're like we learn all
this technical knowledge and then we
actually have a book on like pharmacy
terms for the lay person like you
actually have to like go through that
process you're like oh i'm up here and
they're like we don't know what that is
and you're like okay
yeah the person's at the counter like
can you explain that one more time but
just with a lot less words yeah let me
tell you the path of physiology on this
just like what what does that even mean
i feel like sorry about that
it makes you feel better
right right right cool cool all right
jerry um so let's uh just double check
in we are recording i'm recording my
audio excellent excellent so ladies and
gentlemen welcome to the junkyard love
podcast i'm happy you're here today i'm
here with jerry hello jerry i'm i'm
happy that you're here um let's go ahead
and just start right out the bat with a
little bit of your bio um who you are
what it is that you do and uh
and what we're gonna kind of chat about
today absolutely so the ten word or less
answer uh i had to give for another
pre-interview podcast was um i help
asian american leaders handle conflict
resolution better
uh through coaching
that works yeah
that works
why why why the emphasis on asian
american leadership yeah so
what we like to say in coaching is that
our ideal client is usually who we were
10 years ago
and in my leadership journey which i'm
sure we'll be able to unpack over the
next hour so um you'll
see just exactly how i got into this
space but the biggest uh and or the
biggest point i'm trying to make here is
just that i know what kind of leadership
training i wish i'd had uh in my early
20s
uh late 20s even early 30s and so to
kind of go back down that path and say
hey guys you know i've skinned my knee
plenty of times trying to
find my way forward and now you know let
me do my part to help you not shy away
from your challenges or even provide all
the solutions but to give you the
resources uh so that you can be more
confident in the solutions that you come
up with for yourself as you deal with
life's inevitable challenges
right right yeah my um my ex used to
always remind me and i always really
liked holding on to it when it came to
the podcast and these leadership things
um or giving advice what would my what
would my 16 year old self need to hear
and so i'm always kind of trying to
remember that and the way i'm wording
things or i'm rambling on i always try
to remember okay that's kind of who who
i want my audience to be if i for
whatever reason was 16 and stumbling
through youtube and i found you know me
what would be the things that i would
need to hear so
yeah i think i think that reigns true
you know when we're when we're speaking
to our own individual experience and it
could help um us relate with people a
lot more so um
what is
so so how did you get into this world
let's go right there what what was uh
what was the series of events that kind
of led you to where you're at now
certainly yeah let's uh let me let me
start from the beginning
let's
you know it'll it might not make sense
at first but as the as the uh the play
unfolds you'll you'll be able to see
where everything comes in so
um yeah brace yourself right like they
got the whole 90 minutes let's paint the
whole canvas um
yeah so basically i grew up
uh the son of immigrants uh i still
technically am the son of immigrants but
uh you know we grew up with
the asian mentality of success where
it's like hey find this profitable
reputable
job and that way you get money and
respect
and you need to bring that not only for
yourself but for your family
because you know this is as immigrants
this is what we have to fight for and so
with that mentality right i by default
felt like an outsider and
you know in feeling like an outsider and
trying to get along with people and just
trying to do my best to fit in right you
start to kind of get in some bad habits
like people pleasing like just trying
not to upset anybody or when someone's
upset with you you know you placate them
as best you can even if it comes at
great cost to your own self-respect
and you just feel resentful later and
you just say well hopefully i'll get
over this so all that to kind of set the
stage properly to say hey
um my parents kind of said well you know
go into healthcare pretty much it was
like yeah like you want to be a doctor
right your cousins are doctors and you
know you want the good life that comes
with uh doctor reputation and income and
i said yeah sure you know i didn't like
anything else
so i just said well yeah let me try this
pre-med path for right now
and when i got to college
i learned quickly just how
uh little i actually
uh was interested in pursuing this
partly because i got to see an organic
chemistry you know and it was just kind
of like uh oh right if you have if you
don't have a clear idea on why you want
to become a doctor right if you don't
have a clear idea to say hey i want to
help you know
malnourished kids in like third world
countries right like you're not going to
power through all the hoops that you
have to jump through
in becoming a doctor and i had friends
that did and so you know happy that they
got the career that they're looking for
to fulfill their what they consider
their their own purpose but for me
uh i it was a definitely a sobering
moment i had to ask myself well what do
i really want to do um at that stage in
my life because i still wanted to do
health care but i didn't like the idea
of failure i didn't like the idea of you
know getting wait-listed or even
rejected from med school and so i just
really was like i don't want to
persevere that much i like the idea of
being a doctor more than actually
becoming a doctor doing the work with
that so i said well you know
uh pharmacy
seems like a good profession uh it seems
very clean
and with the right job you can get
pretty good hours and quality of life so
i said you know what
my grandpa being a doctor i had some
interest in health care so maybe this is
just another way in so let me pursue
pharmacy school and
in pharmacy school managed to you know
get the grades i needed to got licensed
and
all that to say in the
pharmacy work settings that i was used
to which is mainly chain pharmacies uh
leadership was not something that was
um desirable because it just seemed like
it was a lot of headaches
for not a lot of extra money it's just
like you had all the scrutiny all the
liability you had to deal with bosses
that were yelling at you about numbers
being low or you know things not going
according to plan and you and you just
said well you know what i i'm my life
isn't worth these headaches so i'm just
gonna avoid them
and
it's nice to learn how to fly under the
radar a little bit but at the same time
you're not growing right i got
comfortable
um working for this chain pharmacy after
i got out of school and just being you
know kind of a bigger fish in the
smaller pond and my boss my boss was
happy with me because she knew i worked
hard um but i wouldn't want i would
never be interested in taking on a
leadership position in a chain pharmacy
just because there's just yeah too many
headaches and so at a point where i was
at five years
with this company but i've had enough i
just said you know um i don't care what
kind of benefits
you're throwing at me it doesn't matter
that i just earned a third week of
vacation
if the other 49 suck right like i'm not
going to stick around
and so
the interesting thing was i had gotten
comfortable
and you know i was able to avoid
conflict and even though i've struggled
with conflict at that point in my life
you know i was just like well i'm bad at
it i'm just gonna not deal with it same
thing with leadership i said oh you know
i tried a couple of times i'm not good
at this i guess i'll never be good at
this i just had a very uh limited view
of my capabilities as a person uh with
certain things that i struggled with
initially and so when i decided to leave
this job to pursue something in teaching
because i hadn't been more intentional
with my career choices and development i
didn't really have any options because i
didn't have any postgrad training in
order to become a professor at a
university or things like that
uh but my one lifeline
was a friend who worked for a consulting
company a pharmacy consulting company uh
here in houston and she said hey i know
you want to teach you don't have
the presidency or the postdoc in order
to teach at a conventional university
but my previous teaching position is
open since i got promoted would you be
interested in applying for this and i
said absolutely so i'm moving from
tennessee to
houston for this job i walked away from
full-time you know pay and benefits to
take on this part-time position and i
would have to earn my way up and
initially being as short-sighted as i
was i said wow this is hopefully the
last company ever have to work for i'm
going to houston i got some friends here
you know i i was just so excited for the
change
and then 11 months later i got fired
and you know that was uh
at the time it was the toughest wake-up
call i'd ever got because i didn't want
to admit that i had there was some sense
of you know feeling entitled and making
excuses
that were kind of bubbling to the
surface because i was able to do better
than like 60 of my you know workforce at
this chain pharmacy but now when my own
flaws are magnified all of a sudden this
company was actually kind enough to tell
me after 11 months no what you're doing
is not working and you're done here and
so
um at the time it hurt a lot because
what was it going to do right rent don't
stop just because you had a bad day
and so
uh
looking for work in a city i didn't have
a lot of career networking in was very
difficult and that's when the roller
coaster started to get really weird
in that uh the next job i ended up at
i was working for a
basically house of cards pharmacy where
filling for crooked doctors and my
paychecks were bouncing so that was also
not great
yeah just one two punch right you're
just like not only am i jeopardizing my
license i'm not even paying my bills
because this guy is just like pocketing
all the money and uh at that stage i had
a very misguided view of grace and to
say well you know he's not honoring his
part but i need to honor my part and
everyone else is around me it's just
like jerry like this is bad for your
license and you're not getting paid
leave like if he's not paying you leave
and so after nine months of that um
thankfully my friends got me out of that
job and got me onto a company that was
more reliable but they was still
struggling and
yeah after a month or two getting going
through training and stuff like that
they said hey we like you but we can't
pay you more than eight hours a week
and i said uh-oh
um do i choose between renting groceries
this month what do i do right not very
sustainable exactly
and so they said well you can get more
hours uh covering for us out at our
austin location
um you know if you're if you're willing
and so i said okay i
i'm going to austin i baggers can't be
choosers so you know and my friends just
are telling me you know you could end up
in worse locations right and i said
yeah and
but i had no idea what my life is going
to look like this point all i know is i
need to pay my bills so i'm out there
you know working it was a great job
don't get me wrong like the team that i
i walked into was wonderful uh but you
know i had no there was no stability
right i wasn't even officially in
payroll
i had no benefits i had nothing of the
stability that i knew i needed that i
didn't appreciate until after i left all
that
and so this is 2012 now and
that summer i got an email from some
friends of mine who
run a pharmacy leadership nonprofit
associated with my pharmacy fraternity
and they said hey
we know that you've been facilitating
workshops on the fraternity side
but we need someone to help out on the
leadership side for our national meeting
this year
and a spot opened up because someone had
to back out would you be willing to step
in
and i said absolutely and so
with that
um you know teaching leadership and then
seeing it modeled for me with a partner
who really brought out the best in me
you know kind of opened my mind a little
bit and
i gave her i gave permission uh myself
permission to give that possibility
because before you know it was like oh
leadership is hard i could never be good
at it i'll never be good at it and it's
like well you know if that's what you
say about yourself how's that working
out for you if you say you can't be a
good leader who am i to question that
right
but if i said now
well what if i could be a good leader
what would that look like what kind of
work would that involve
and so now i came back to work with you
know this renewed vigor and this
excitement and so the company i was
working for at the time said okay about
a month later they said well
you have the option of staying part-time
in austin or you can go to houston for a
full-time manager position uh since that
opened up and
right now ironically enough the first
three months i was living in austin
jacob like i was like oh you know i'm
just
this isn't home and
right as i thought i was actually going
to lay down roots in austin and that's
something i got to know some great guys
and you know getting to know the city a
little better things like that um you
know
i i knew that i couldn't stay
comfortable and i knew i wanted to come
back home to houston need to take on
this leadership challenge i didn't want
to avoid this anymore and so
next thing i know i'm packing up all my
things and coming back to houston
and
things didn't get easier jacob you know
i i struggle i still struggled with
conflict they still struggled to uh you
know confront underperforming
technicians i still
um you know didn't know how to
uh see firing as a loving thing just
recognizing hey you know what you're
doing here isn't working here we're not
necessarily accusing you of like being
this terrible person you just need to
find a company that's willing to put you
know maybe tailor themselves around your
preferences and your styles like that's
and that's like the high end that's very
much benefit of the doubt kind of
situation but you have to at the end of
the day like the relationship is going
to work out but i actually got written
up because i wasn't writing my
technicians up now i'm just like oh my
gosh like when will this get easier when
will this get better
and so the company actually had their
funding pulled a month a year later
uh just because the business model was
uh not sustainable basically um
just a quick aside for people and
they're like why did this happen
so
the company was involved in pain
management medications in a legitimate
way like they had a department of public
safety officer you know a former one
helping us keep in line to stay out of
trouble but the problem is if the dea
still doesn't like you
and they you know get in the way and
interfere with your ability to keep
medications in stock uh you can't sell
what you don't have and you know if you
can't make money the owners will move on
so
interestingly enough the only reason i
even get an interview at my next job was
that i had leadership experience on my
resume now because of my time you know
being a manager for this company and i
said wow you know that was a good
decision i'm glad that i can you know
get the attention of more companies now
that i have leadership experience so the
first thing i usually tell people is
that leadership saved my career uh it is
my one of my biggest struggles and
biggest fascinations now and which is
why i got into that space but to finish
up that story right what i tell people
is that farmers the pharmacy jobs that
they have are like icebergs and that
it's like they melt after like one or
two years you know it's just like that's
it they're just gone
and so on one hand i have more icebergs
to pick from but there's still icebergs
and so the next couple years are more of
the same like i'd find a company you
know barely in time to keep gainful
employment and then after a year or two
they would go away and so about four
years ago when my previous company went
under um i just had to ask myself well
you know i'm tired of chasing scripts
from doctors i'm tired of fighting
insurance companies that determine how
much i make on these medications even
though i'm putting in the same amount of
work
but
i love teaching leadership workshops i
love developing people
what if i tried to make a career out of
developing people so i started talking
to coaches and other people in this
space to see you know exactly how how do
you do this
and i knew i'd gotten pretty good at
facilitating uh and running workshops
and things like that but i still had no
idea how to open a business run a
business build a business and so i
stayed away from actually throwing my
hat in the ring for quite some time and
it wasn't until coveted hit where i said
well i can't afford to put this off any
longer like i
i still have this day job as a
pharmacist which i'm grateful for don't
get me wrong but uh i know my long-term
trajectory is to get this side business
off the ground and really have more of
an impact for people that i know need
this kind of help yeah
yeah right wow man what what what a
journey i feel like so much uh forced
forced learning
experiences you know i mean so so would
you say that you
would you say that you're someone who
wouldn't consider yourself a born leader
but more of like a learned leader or
do you have any distinction between the
two oh that's a that's a great question
and it is an ongoing debate um i
actually heard uh i was reminded of a
phrase recently that maxwell uses in one
of his books and he talks about what is
he addressing the question what how do
you how do you resolve whether or not
leaders are born or made
and uh his simple answer is of course
leaders are born how else are they made
right it's just like well but in all
seriousness
um
i think part of it just comes back down
to what do you believe about leadership
right
um if you believe that leadership is
innate to some people and exclusive to
them and you know cut off from others
like what chance do you have
right
but if you're willing to believe the
idea that
um leadership is a skill that i can
learn if i and improve that if i put
enough work in
like would i even allow for that
possibility
and you know if leaders are born and not
made
you know
why why don't we even bother right but
um you know it's i think about maxwell's
uh elaboration on that topic and he goes
you know hey look
there's three types of people when it
comes to leadership the first are hey
people have innate talent
and you know they act on it great
most people fall in the middle group
number two group which is hey they may
not have all the instincts or innate
talent that the first group has but they
still have enough to work with that they
can improve upon right and then he says
then the third just don't care and he
says take heart that you're not one of
them because they wouldn't have picked
up this book so you know nice nice uh
sales pitch there it's just like hey
don't worry feel good about yourself
that you even care to buy my book so
good job um
but yeah with all that said yeah i mean
it took time uh for sure and it's still
a process i'm far from done in terms of
my abilities as a leader i see it every
day at my day job just when i thought i
had everything in place so that my you
know team would really do the work and
be more autonomous on their part and
they keep falling back into bad habits
and you know
um it's like we talked about this like i
thought i was better at this
but for some reason i have to do a lot
more maintenance on my team than i ever
expected but i say this not to sound
entitled uh it's just an opportunity to
learn and say okay well i guess i'm just
not done uh i need to keep finding ways
to motivate them well so here we go
right yeah i mean and that's what it
takes for as a leader you got to kind of
like take on the the workload on your
shoulders okay we're underperforming in
this area we're not doing well in this
area or where this could be improved how
can i make that better
like what what am i doing that could be
changed like how could i do what i'm
doing differently to help my team you
know i think that's what it takes to be
a leader i also think that being a
leader isn't really a
i mean it's such a broad word in many
ways but it really isn't something that
you arrive at it's a constant it's a
it's a way of making decisions
of of constantly like egg every day so
so how would a leader
make this decision you know when
something comes up
maybe you have a
an automatic reaction uh here's how i
want to react here's what would be
comfortable here's what's going to keep
me in this spot or you can think like a
leader okay what what does the team need
how are we going to grow how does this
lead us to our next step you know how
how can we how can i lean down and offer
a hand to the rest of my team to to
bring them up so for me um
leadership has always been very
fascinating to me so i always liked it i
was a um in in 10th grade i was a
sophomore class president in high school
yeah oh yeah thank you um
but it was
i i remember i actually had this moment
where the like the vice principal
stopped me and we were going into one of
the school dances
and as we were walking and i was
watching walking in with a couple of the
other guys and to be honest i feel like
we were probably we're probably like out
in the car drinking or smoking or
something like we were something fun
yeah yeah yeah so i in you know it's
funny i think that the the vice
principal that that that i'm referencing
um he basically walked in and he kind of
pulled me to the side and i feel like he
probably knew like he probably smelled
my breath he you know i mean he probably
understood it but he kind of gave me
this couple minute long
it caught me off guard but it always
stuck with me and he pretty much like
was looking in the eye and just hey i
don't know if you noticed but you're a
leader people look up to you people
listen to what you what you have to say
and it was so heavy like i i i mean i
probably at the moment i was probably
like okay man sure for sure
but then you know it did stick with me
in a way that as i got older um and as i
i do find myself in leadership roles or
supervising or managing any of these
roles i am i keep it in the back of my
mind this
okay if if people are listening to me
you know if people are going to take
time out of their day to to stop what
they're doing or if i'm rambling on
about something i look around and
everybody's staring at me and they're
actually intently listening to what i'm
saying maybe i should provide them with
good content you know maybe i should
maybe i should find ways to be helpful
maybe i could improve my
what i know so the things that i'm
speaking or the the situations that i am
actually leading um
can can you know be be helpful and
beneficial to to the people involved so
it has been this interesting um
that one moment really really stood out
for me um and and so so i try to
i don't know if leaders are born i i
don't know if that really it just
doesn't really seem to answer the
question you know it seems i think we
all kind of have
some form of leadership within us and i
think if you can put yourself into the
right environment put yourself into the
right niche
train yourself in the right ways
put yourself around around the correct
people who who need to hear your message
or hear hear your way of leadership in
in your your way of um
teaching them and leading the charge so
to say
um yeah i think we all i think we all
kind of have
a leader within us what do you think
about that jerry do you think everybody
kind of has a point in them that's
leader oh absolutely um i
because honestly if leaders are born and
not made why i mean why do we sell so
many leader development programs like if
you're basically it's just like this is
just an exercise in futility you know
yeah thanks for your money you know good
luck
um
i
honestly there's this funny paradox of
you know you hear so many people say you
know my mentor saw something in me i
couldn't see myself
right
and so it's like well how you know how
do you want to respond to that you know
do you just say nah i you know
he's he's a pretty smart guy but i think
i know myself better and even in
coaching when we say hey look you're the
expert on your life right uh at the same
time
i believe a good mentor good influence
is always going to see your potential
more than actually just what's already
there right they see what could be and
not just what it is
they acknowledge both but uh i mean i've
it would take a lot and don't get me
wrong there are people i've mistakenly
written off you know over the years but
then you know you find out later oh my
gosh like i had no idea like what they
accomplished and you know what they're
doing with their lives now right um
on one hand everyone loves an underdog
story on the other hand you know
everyone
i do believe i do like i i believe that
everyone has that potential if they're
willing to act on it it's just that's
really the biggest tiebreaker it's not a
question of whether or not you have it
it's just a question of whether or not
you want to build on it and act on it in
a way that's actually going to have an
impact the way that will actually you
know kind of elevate the playing field
right yeah lift everybody up get
everybody else on board and improved and
everyone's you know working hard and
motivated and appreciative and
respectful i would love to see that
right right well okay so so how do we
lean into it if we're someone who's
listening and they're like maybe they
have some sort of leadership qualities
maybe they've been a leader in the past
maybe they're at a point where they're
looking around and they've they've kind
of taken you know maybe maybe a more
beta role maybe they they want to step
up maybe they want to start feeding that
that good wolf i like to say you know
that that that
future that long-term version of
ourselves rather than that short-term
comfort version of ourselves so if we do
have some spark of leadership someone
maybe is resonating with this how do we
feed that beast how do we feed the
correct piece and be a leader yeah yeah
good good question um i think the first
thing i would think
to ask them is to say hey you know who's
in your circle that you respect
right like who's who's someone in your
current circle right now that you would
say you know what they have qualities
that i want to have and i want to learn
how to have them
what would it take for you to just
hit them up for coffee
to say hey can i
just borrow you for 30 minutes and
interview you because i noticed that hey
you know you're really patient under
under pressure you're really forgiving
you have a level of compassion that i
wish i had
you know
can i just pick your brain for 30
minutes and see what would it take for
you know to learn how you got to that
point
um because you know on one hand i would
love to
you know get the attention of simon
sinek or all these other thought leaders
out there right but they're pretty busy
and i'm not you know i'm exactly on
their radar but you don't have to go to
the top top right you just need someone
that's in your in your neighborhood
right that you like and so just
start with your network right start
where you are and just say hey who's
someone i want to learn from and just if
you have their contact information you
know it's warm traffic right it's
they're they're not you're not cold
calling it's just
not hard to just pick up that phone or
send that email and fire off that text
and just say hey
let me pick your brain and learn from
you for 30 minutes i think that would be
the next action i would recommend for
anyone trying to start
yeah no i think that's a perfect idea
too jay because we i think when we look
closely if we take take a step back and
also look closely at the same time you
know we can kind of look around and i
bet you most of us are
if we looked a little bit we would find
people in our lives who we do have um
traits they have traits we admire you
know
i feel as i've gotten older um and i'm
able to kind of retrospectively look
back at you know my teenage years and in
how i learned because i was very
observant i would i would watch the
people around me because you know i was
very much um you know building my own my
own puzzle piece my own puzzle with all
the pieces sort of so so to say uh i was
learning along the way i was very diy i
was very observant okay how does this
person do that okay i'm gonna try it
that way no it doesn't work for me
whatever um and as i get older i can
kind of really
i admire so many so many people in my
life because i i'll see the way they do
this one thing or the way they they
interact with their family in this way
the way they speak to their wife in this
way the the way that they take care of
their business and this way and i'm it's
really cool because you can kind of
piece together ooh i like that this
person that i admire does that i'm gonna
i'm gonna try that oh and the way that
he handles this i'm gonna try that too
you know so
i think that's a great example of
finding the people in your circle
finding the people who are available to
you and i bet you that you know more
often than not if you kind of just
straight up with someone you tell them
hey
look here's an area of my life that i
want to try to you know buckle down on
here's an area of my life where i'm i'm
just not doing super well um
like let's go to coffee i'll pay for
coffee please like let's just
conversate you know i bet you the the
the person on the other end would be
pretty reciprocating of of being told
that you know that's that'll probably
feel good to know that someone one of
your friends or someone in your life
kind of looks up to you in a certain way
and you have something that they can
offer this is real that's real community
right there you know that's absolutely
yeah yeah
um
so uh you had a quote on your website be
free from the fear of conflict
like it was just this simple thing i was
just kind of browsing through you know
looking on the website and i read that
more than once and i think that that's
actually really really cool because
conflict it's it's something that so
many of us
will repeat the same thing every day
we'll be almost addicted to conflict in
a way you know and it will be
unconscious of it as well we just think
it's part of our everyday life well i'm
talking to susan and every friday susan
ticks me off at work here we go you know
i get every every morning at 8 00 a.m i
talk to jeff and and here we go that's
just the conflict that i deal with with
30 minutes just this thing that
sometimes we can get used to so um being
free from the fear of conflict i i think
not only noticing that conflict is
happening but noticing that you can be
free of it and um noticing that it's you
don't have to be you don't have to be
afraid of it it's something that you can
kind of learn to develop within yourself
and learn to
um
i guess i guess navigate differently so
let's expand on this jerry what's this
uh
be free from the fear of conflict what
does that mean to you yeah jacob i'm so
happy you did homework you know
hold me too hold me to my words yeah i
know absolutely and yeah and uh
trying to get my message across a little
more clearly and straightforward uh
what's interesting right is that in my
attempts to
resolve conflict
what happens when it's resolved you go
you experience closure
and you you feel good that you can have
some level of relief right and guess
what's waiting for you another conflict
and now the stakes are higher right so
the wording is very deliberate in that
you will never be free of conflict
and you may never be free
um
you know from that fear
but you can still deal with it right you
can say hey like you don't have to be
afraid of it anymore um you can
either run from it which never solves
the problem right and you'll probably
lose a lot of relationships and
friendships along the way if you never
uh if you keep avoiding it right and
i've lost friendships that way because i
just said you know what i i can't even
begin to start i'm just gonna have to
drop this one and that's tough because
you know there are some friendships
toxic relationships yeah you just have
to drop and that's just a case-by-case
basis but uh to be able to recognize hey
is this healthy conflict or unhealthy
conflict uh as you start to notice
distinctions the more you lean into this
and so when you realize
for instance you know if we have a good
working relationship and there's
something i did that
i messed up on or was not up to your
expectation the worst thing for you to
do is not to tell me right to say i'll
just get over it it's like no like i
would if if the
if the tough feedback is coming from
someone that i respect and trust
addressing that uh
you know
broken expectation while it's still
small is really the healthiest way to
maintain the relationship right like no
one ever says oh that fire is not big
enough i don't have to put it out yet
but that's exactly what we're dealing
with right now oh no you know that's i
can deal with that later it's like now
you know now everything's burned down
and you're just like oh i guess i should
have just you know put that baking soda
on a little sooner
right right deal with the ashes exactly
um but yeah that's the idea is just to
say hey you know what uh there was a
point where i just said you know
conflict oh like it's just so exhausting
and i know i just don't want to deal
with this anymore but now
uh in asking myself well what are the
blessings that conflict brings to the
table right to recognize that hey you
know what i'm seeing this person for who
they really are and that wow okay now
that the truth is all out now we can
actually build on this relationship and
i had to learn that the hard way several
times just to say hey you know what um
passive aggressive comments are funny in
movies but they're terrible in real life
relationships so
yeah
you know we that's why we have the
movies right to say stuff that we could
never get away with in real life and
people think well you know what i'd love
to say that it's like try that let me
know how that goes right
so to ask people hey what would it take
for you to be able to say hey you know
what we're going to respectfully
disagree on these things but i still
care about you i still respect you
we may not line up on everything but as
long as we know that hey there's a
common goal we agree on that we need to
get done then let's figure out the best
way to do it and i mean i'll give an
example so
i help out with a
a local salsa dancing club at the at the
university uh i graduated from so i rise
i you know they started salsa club and i
and i helped out with and that's you
know one of the one of my favorite joys
in my weeks just to teach students how
to enjoy dance as much as i do and so
the funny thing is um
at one point it was just open source
sharing there were no dues you know
there was no overhead so we didn't have
to charge a lot of money and so just
four people that were generous including
myself were happy to just you know run
lessons and just have people have a good
time and then after a while we just kind
of got sick of the fact that even though
we didn't need a lot of money we liked
having a little money in the bank in
case we wanted to do something or make a
nice purchase or get some nicer
equipment things like that and i went
back and forth with these students
because right i'm out of school i'm like
money is a statement of value and they
say no money is a barrier to entry and
so we had this conflict over whether or
not to charge dues and go back and forth
well you know we don't want to keep
students away and people you know uh
they resent you know they said they feel
resentful and have to pay something just
enjoy it and i say well you know people
don't respect free stuff so how do we
you know navigate all that and it wasn't
for a lack of empathy and so i just said
hey at some point i just kind of
held their feet to the fire and said hey
look we need to address this
even if the answer comes out that the
best answer is no we will keep things
free
so be it i just want us to go through
the process and thank goodness that they
came across a great compromise that for
a solution i wouldn't come up with on my
own and they said okay fine we're going
to keep it free for rice students but
everyone else that's you know kind of
gleaning you know blessing from what
we're doing has to pay like you know
like 15 a semester which is still
nothing for like paying working
professionals right and the funny thing
is when we implemented that plan no one
fought back because you know the
students that couldn't want to keep on
to whatever dollars they have they said
oh this is still free for us because we
already paid all the use all our money
for tuition it's great and then everyone
else you know that was you know paying
you know paying money we said no like 15
bucks for a semester that's it that's a
no-brainer yeah absolutely and now we
have money in the bank and everyone
still comes to our lessons so you know
yeah but yeah had we not addressed that
conflict right uh
you know had we not acknowledged hey we
disagree on these things but what is the
best way forward i mean i'm so grateful
that we came across that solution and
you know we're stronger for it right
yeah but we hadn't it wouldn't have been
if we had been oh that's just a tough
conversation i don't want to have that
it's like no now we have money in the
bank
yeah i mean i mean so often we want to
avoid the tough conversation i've done
it tons of times in my own life of
course you know we all have our own our
own levels of it but it's it's
interesting that i i i think it is very
powerful to make a decision rather than
rather than just the decision of
indecision you know because because
that's also another point that i've
heard i've heard other leaders um kind
of state before is you know the decision
to um
um
enact or the decision to not make a
decision is still a decision right you
know and and sometimes um you don't know
the
the resolutions that are on the other
side of just having that that
conversation you know you guys came up
with something
new that wasn't even in the original
kind of disagreement what did the um
because when it comes down to the nitty
gritty of actually like face to face
with people you're working with with
people you're around
looking them in the eye not not having
any passive aggressiveness not you know
really leaving it all on the table not
having our emotions get the best of us
all sorts of sorts of these things what
does it really look like or what did it
look like in that situation
of actually being able for you to say
look guys
this is clearly plaguing us this is a
decision that we need to come to
so so the actual boots on the ground
conversation how did that go
yeah um i think
one of the
one of the best uh solutions i kind of
stumbled into in when we finally all got
on a zoom call to discuss everything was
number one for me to acknowledge
uh the strong points of their argument
right
because that shows a level of respect
and attention and empathy saying hey
i am paying attention to what you're
actually saying
um
and
to be able to say hey look guys like
here is where we were
these were the strong points this is the
case uh to keep that going to say hey
you know what we're just about sharing
and it doesn't cost us a lot to share so
let's just keep sharing and that's
basically you know their mentalities and
they said hey we have a you know good
nucleus of people for right now this
solution will work
and then you know from my standpoint to
be able to say hey look guys
my stance in light of this is to say
well you know i'm happy to be generous
and i also want some indication that my
time experience and effort are worth
something and
um you know and making the case that hey
people take this more seriously and will
have less attrition if people have skin
in the game so given all these strengths
that sometimes may feel like they're at
odds
how do we address this and to dovetail
on that quickly right there
there's an interesting thing that
happens when you acknowledge the other
side's strengths right number one it
diffuses the argument any any kind of
like antagonism because people realize
oh
we don't have to dig our heels in
right he already understands and
appreciates what we bring to the table
and oh yeah that means we're on the same
side we're all working toward a common
goal of trying to keep this club viable
so how do we just do that um i was
re-listening to a book called decisive
by chip and dan heath and they talk
about the situation and i'm glad i
managed to review it right before this
podcast they talk about
this company that had a mind that was
not doing well financially and you know
the executives want to close it because
it is financially uh in the red but then
all the employees of the mine are saying
no you need to keep it open you know we
have bills today we have you know mouths
to feed
and so you know this new executive comes
in
and challenges them and says well hey
guys let's look at all the options on
the table and i want you to ask yourself
what would it take for each option to be
the best option and all of a sudden it
the conflict shifted from antagonizing
to collaborative and productive conflict
because now
people are advocating you know now the
now the miners have to ask themselves
well what would it be you know if we had
to close the mic what would what would
have to be true for closing mine to be
the best decision for this company right
or same thing with keeping it open to
say hey you know if we were to keep the
mine open what would what kind of
numbers would they need to hit in order
to for us to reconsider closing the mind
right and so the interesting thing and
enough was interestingly enough
after all this deliberation they
realized no we're going to have to close
its mind so even the miners
understood they say hey it sucks but we
understand that we have to close this
mind and we're going to have to deal
with the next actions for everybody that
will be affected by it right all of a
sudden you're sitting there thinking oh
my gosh like i don't even know how it
started so how did not study this
example
man i'm so glad that i don't have to
make all the mistakes to learn from in
order to be effective right i can study
this one and share with other people so
anyway yeah
no no
that one is perfect to get everybody
else's mind on board you know and uh
and again have that difficult
conversation i'm sure this was probably
a long elaborated conversation i don't
know how they uh painted it in the book
but yeah um
yeah yeah because the
you know passive aggressiveness as well
as people-pleasing going back to that
word i mean you you mentioned it before
i think that is that is a huge one i
i deal with i deal with
people pleasing fairly often um just my
own versions of it because i'm i've
always been this chameleon personality
um
i have my i have my natural state and i
feel like you know if like me me out in
the woods by myself um you know that
that's that's a different person than
you're going to get when i'm social for
for a couple days and around people i
just really like reflecting people's um
personalities back to them and
reciprocating and i don't know just just
seems to be my natural state of being
but it makes me being a chameleon and
mirroring other people
often does put me in a place of people
pleasing where i'm just kind of looking
where what does this other person want
and i've kind of learned how i've gotten
that way and and how my my development
as a as a young person has um how it was
helpful to me as a younger person and
how it's unhelpful and helpful to me as
i get older so it's always a
a stepping stone i'm trying to navigate
um
but the when it comes to people pleasing
what what do you find the people that
you're coaching um even in your own life
how do we
not only learn about it but how do we
kind of improve on this you know stand
up for ourselves a little bit more um
really listen to our our inner guidance
and and speak up
yeah yeah great great i love these
questions because it is i think this is
even if you feel good actually feel like
you're good at conflict right like how
can you not you know glean something
about reviewing fundamentals or trying
to still get better at it right because
as you said leadership is a lifelong
skill and conflict resolution is no
different
um i think the first is just to yeah
generate that level of awareness right
what am i feeling right now like if
something if promise it feels like it's
broken you know what how do i feel it
why
and to be able to be willing to say
um you know if i keep this inside me it
doesn't do any good i think that was
really one of my biggest turning points
in conflict resolution was recognizing
if i am frustrated the worst thing i can
do is just suppress it and try to
dissipate it on my own um and then the
second mistake is to talk to everyone
else around the conflict and
you know so it's one thing to like get
it out in the open but if it's not with
the person that you need to resolve the
conflict with that's also unproductive
right um and so to be able to say hey
you know what um i can't afford to
tolerate this i think that's the first
thing to realize about yourself to say
hey you know what um there is something
broken and i can't afford to let it sit
because if i do i'm just to get more and
more resentful and i've seen that time
and time again people just need to ask
themselves what's the cost of inaction
as i said earlier and so the second is
okay if this is out and about
now
do i recognize that the person i need to
dress with is a collaborator you know is
a teammate is a friend and
you know the best thing for our
relationship is for me to be honest i do
need to learn how to be tactful right
unless it's a level of bluntness that
both people can appreciate and are
willing to like you know uh understand
hey you know what i might this might
come across a little rough but i'd
rather say it than not right um so the
second is okay i can't tolerate inaction
um if i care enough about this person
and care enough about the relationship i
need to go ahead and directly address it
with the problem with them
and then from there just to say hey you
know what
i'm not sure why i'm having these
feelings but these are my feelings and i
need to share them with you because um
help me process the story behind them
help me understand this right because
that's one of the
quote trump cards that people use in
health resolution say hey they can't
refute how you feel like they they might
disagree with it but they can't refute
that and you have to use that very
carefully because on one hand just
trying to be honest but you can't afford
to be manipulative right that's that's
the other that's the other big mistake i
think that people when it comes to this
but i think the initial response to your
question is to say yeah um generate that
awareness uh recognize that um you have
to do something about it and then also
to remember hey
this is not about my ego this is about
trying to
agree on and honor a higher standard
between me and the person that i need to
trust us with and i think that's a good
start
yeah yeah i i definitely like that when
it comes to
i feel like our emotions often get in
the way right is that something that you
that you find often you have to
to bring shine a little light on bring
awareness around
um of of maybe people not even
recognizing when their emotions are are
getting the best of them when emotions
because if if i start getting angry and
i'm i'm trying to solve a conflict and i
start getting overly emotional or
erratic or whatever sometimes the other
person is going to mirror it you know
and we're going to we're going to kind
of activate each other in an unnecessary
way
do you have any um
in any resolutions for people who who
might be needing to either
notice that they're having an emotional
response or even just if they do already
know that they they have it how do they
kind of keep it under under control
under underlocking yeah yeah it's it's
uh
it's definitely not a one-size-fits-all
kind of answer but i think for the
truest principles for anybody
you know for some people they say hey
let me just journal like right now just
let me mental rammed up on a piece of
paper this is what happened this is what
i'm feeling because the sooner you give
yourself
the sooner you get it out of your head
and into a third person state right you
can kind of be more objective with
evaluating your situation uh so that's
one approach that might work for some
people other people might need 24 hours
right just to say hey you know what let
me
let me um sit and process this
um and calm down and kind of get it out
of my let that right out of my system
before i can get back to a rational way
of thinking because i think
while we can't
you know do away with them completely i
think it's i think it's foolish just to
completely disregard them or you know to
like ignore them because we're human
like we have feelings we have emotions
but to channel them in a way that's
still ultimately constructive because
yeah like on one hand hey your emotions
and feelings might be telling you
something about the situation maybe
maybe it's just that like for me right
if someone breaks the promise i feel
disrespected that's the first thing uh
that i feel i feel disrespected because
it says hey you made this promise even
if you didn't keep it as originally uh
intended like my expectations that you
still find a way to honor it that you
you know communicate with me proactively
why you couldn't honor it and that we
make you know alternate arrangements and
it's not without grace like you
obviously you know want to be more
accommodating because yeah like life
happens family emergencies come up so
it's not fair for me to completely judge
them based on my understanding of the
situation but i do believe hey you know
what your emotions are telling you
something so yeah don't disregard them
but study them but also don't let them
affect how you respond to other
situations and so if you need to take a
day before addressing a situation you
don't want to wait too long obviously
because resentment just festers but hey
let them know hey i you know this
happened i'm going give me a day
and then i'll i'll reach back out again
to you and then we'll be able to assess
and and uh you know collaborate so
something like that right right yeah i
mean i think a lot of people be
surprised how how different our
reactions to something are going to be
if we just give it 24 hours so we just
give it a little bit of time to to cool
off let whatever biochemical responses
that were happening in that moment kind
of settle all right let's get clear
minded what do i really think about that
what do i really desire out of that
situation what do we what what's the
best for our overall you know um
community in in this situation our whole
group our whole team uh jerry do you do
you watch uh
just think about someone who's a
conflict resolution coach do you
how do you feel when you watch things
like the presidential debate um like
like the more recent one like where
they're
they're not
even communicating they're just kind of
attacking each other and it's just just
so silly i imagine
with all of your your experience in this
in this realm you probably just oh man
you guys are doing everything wrong how
do you feel when you watch stuff like
that
uh a couple thoughts number one it makes
me sad right that you like these these
people have come along so far in life
and then you decide to default to really
bad and childish and immature habits um
yeah i i won't i don't want to
again in my desire to avoid unnecessary
conflict i don't want to get overly
political but at the same time i can i
can honestly say hey look you know i've
seen enough evidence to know
you know the fact that there are people
out there that deliberately
uh pray on discord and like to like to
antagonize in an attempt to make an us
versus them mentality
you know and it's not just for like the
you know recent presidential elections
this is i see it true i've seen that
you're on my work team i had to fire a
technician a couple years ago because
she actively sewed discord because she
was more concerned about looking like
the best person for the job because she
wanted to actively sabotage everybody
else
and it was
maddening that she felt like that she
had to do this and even worse she was
taking on work that she couldn't handle
herself and anytime she messed up she
would keep it to herself because she
didn't want to deal with the fallout
that was that she feared if she found if
we found out the bosses found out that
she was not doing her job and you know
it was just a just a really destructive
cycle and so yes anytime people like let
their ego get in the way of these things
um to a point where it's more about like
how you hurt me as opposed to hey let's
let's let's agree on and accept this
standard to make sure hey let's keep
this company open right like we can't
afford to
we have enough missiles firing out our
ship outside of us we can't afford to be
syncing our own boat right but that's
exactly what people do it's versus the
problem yeah exactly it's like yeah you
know we can handle any missile that
comes at us but you know it's not if we
don't have a boat to
to float then no like the missiles the
missile will only just you know
add to the the problems already here so
yeah let's let's straighten things out
internally for sure yeah yeah it kind of
reminds me of have you ever watched game
of thrones
uh just clips
just clips okay yeah basically um i mean
you definitely can't summarize game of
thrones it's a very very elaborate show
but but the the point that i was um
glancing towards in this is uh one of
the main characters jon snow
there's there's something going on
there's something bigger than the
who's gonna get to sit in the iron
throne like who gets the chair who's
who's the king because it's like the
king thing doesn't matter when you know
global warming is coming or the the in
in game of thrones the king doesn't
matter when there's like these white
walkers zombie type things that are
gonna kind of come and just destroy all
of us it doesn't matter who's sitting on
the throne when there's nobody left to
sit on the throne you know exactly
yeah so we we get kind of lost in the in
in the weeds there and uh for getting
forgetting what's important for sure
absolutely yeah you're just like so what
if you won like they're about you know
if even if she even thought this
technician managed to get everyone else
fired so she could be you know still be
around it's like the company had to shut
down because of all the stuff that you
messed up it's like okay well you have
to move on anyway yeah you know good
luck
well so so in that specific situation um
i'm not sure like how much you can
indulge in that what was going on in her
i mean this is a strange way to wear it
but what was going on in her head you
know like what what what do you see as
someone who is a a conflict resolution
coach you know with your experience um
with your ability to to you know
probably read people pretty well um i'm
sure that that ability is improving more
and more too but
what what would you say was going on
with her like what was she trying to get
or not get or yeah uh no it's um there
are no names so i can i can hear all the
dirty launches there's no names um
and plus you know in the event that she
is listening hey you know i'll say hey
you know i hope you're doing well and
you know i hope you were able to learn
from this and grow as a person you know
so hey no no ill will i hope nothing
comes across as sub tweeting or like
dancing in anyone's grave because i am
sad that you know we had to have this
come to this moment of closure even if
it was an outcome that she may have
disagreed with but yeah it comes back
down to
um thinking that the best way to get
ahead is to sabotage others is to just
make others look bad or you know if you
like to get paid but don't really want
to do the work that's involved there's
some kind of broken
thinking involved right that just says
hey you know i'm doing a good job and no
one needs to let me know how i'm messing
up because i don't want to feel like
incompetent because i have mistakes to
learn from or things to improve upon
unless i need to do some like uh
customer service level or you know
damage control or you know spin doctor
thing just to kind of smooth over my
mistakes
um yeah so when people
don't
uh remove their ego from the situation
like i tell people i say look um
i'm not worried about getting credit if
i get the work done
and i do a good job and i make things
easier for other people to do their work
more effectively credit will find me and
of course i'm just going to deflect it
back to my team and say hey you know
what this is nice thank you for this i
couldn't have done it without their help
right
but for people who feel like they have
to spotlight all the work that they're
doing and
uh you know are afraid for job security
if they don't you know have the do the
heaviest lifting things like that or you
know hide things the fact that anyone
needs to hide anything is really the
biggest red flag right when they feel
like oh you know i'm just going to keep
this to myself and hopefully people
won't find out how bad a problem it is
until like the bomb like eventually
blows up that when i'm not there or i'm
after i'm fired because you know after
after we dismissed her you know we found
out
everything oh we had to do a whole ton
of cleanup after the first in the next
two months because of everything that
she was hiding that she was you know
making you know bad promises for because
she couldn't handle it on her own and
yeah so this unwillingness to delegate
unwillingness to communicate um in her
mind where she feels like yeah i have to
make myself look good and i have to
justify myself this way as opposed to
taking the feedback and being humble and
coachable and when the company says hey
look this is
this is the system you're gonna have to
buy into if you're gonna be here and if
you trust us enough uh that you know
we're not we don't wanna we're not gonna
dismiss your opinions um but at the same
time we need you to consider our
feedback uh and how you want to act on
this if you expect the team to really
flourish in a way so you're not burnt
out you don't feel like you have to hide
anything and you're going to be willing
to receive feedback that you may not
like as long as you understand that this
is in your best interest right we want
to tell you how to stay employed with
this company and you know
and i had to do it again with my text
recently even after we thought we
cleaned house there's some people that
are still reverting to bad habits and
again it's like hey the most loving
thing i can do for you is tell you
exactly what you need to do to improve
like i'd rather ask questions and let
you discover for yourself but in this
moment if it's too urgent okay we're
gonna give you some directives and the
clarity that you say you need so that
this doesn't happen again
yeah yeah and i think also being able to
to ask for help you know that's such a
hard thing too yeah this i mean if you
recognize that you're in an environment
where um you know your leadership team
or just your team around you is willing
to
really like listen and really um you
know not not brush you off or any of
those sorts of things if if there's an
environment where you feel comfortable
and safe saying
you guys i i just don't know i need some
help for this you know that's that's a
good thing so recognizing if you do have
that environment around or some um
doorway to to those sort of
conversations like definitely definitely
take it on because there's no shame in
in saying hey look i i don't want to
make this a bigger deal than it is um
you know i think there is part of it
that
it does kind of hurt to admit that we're
not as competent as as maybe we put on
to be you know i i think we all have our
own our own um
you know our own fear of inadequacy
for those sorts of things but but it is
a powerful i i would say that it takes
um courage is is a good word for that if
you're the person who needs help
having the courage to ask for help
having the courage to say you guys have
kind of dug myself into a hole i'm so
sorry that we're all gonna have to work
a little bit harder for the next couple
days but it's gonna save us you know
from having months long of work i think
that that's really worth it and that is
something worth worth leaning into it's
good to have that courage to say i need
some help
yeah absolutely yeah the last thing we
would want is for people to think no i
i don't have any blind spots i i'm
perfectly competent to handle everything
you throw at me and it's like
that's that can work up to an extent but
if you're honestly taking more than you
can honestly handle it's silly and
foolish to say no boss yeah i'll figure
out a way to get it right instead of
being able to uh kindly negotiate well
boss you know this is what you have me
working on here and then you have you
know project b and c and d now you want
me to take on project e so
based on
a b c and d
like what do you want me to
kind of shelve or put off for right now
so i can focus on e if this is really
the most urgent thing right instead of
just being like no boss you know
conflict of version right oh yeah boss
just keep giving whatever you want me
i'll get it done i can handle it yeah
yeah and then you're up getting no sleep
and you're yeah you're in you're
stressed out and it's just adding up and
yeah and then you then you you kind of
half ass a few things rather than whole
asking one thing you know as they say
um
hey i did want to go it sounds like you
um are well versed in the uh literature
world so do you have book
recommendations i always love to get
book recommendations from
jacob you're speaking my language what
do you got man what do you got
and what what have you been reading
lately as well yeah um
so
some of my favorite books um
there are five books by the heath
brothers that i think every leader in
established consider reading they are
made to stick
power of moments switch decisive and
upstream and all five of them have
compelling examples and will really
inspire you to to really uh just do some
amazing things with your life um michael
bungie stanier wrote two books for
coaching one uh the first one is the
coaching habit talking about the seven
questions leaders can ask to uh you know
not
uh get burnt out uh you know
compensating for every team mistake that
new team makes uh the second uh by him
is called the advice trap and
recognizing hey your advice actually
isn't helping as much as you think it is
you know just because you think you have
the right answer doesn't mean they're
going to use it or apply it the way you
think it's best you know um
getting things done on the productivity
side getting things done by david allen
he you can get certified in his
productivity methods it's just this
really crazy global movement
um i also like
um atomic habits james clear he does a
good job just yeah just tailoring you
know how do i what are the four aspects
of making sure i get a happy stick i
recently finished limitless by jim quick
that's k-w-i-k
uh really great story really simple uh
fundamentals on on how to really unlock
your mind power
and i'm i've finished a couple business
books uh donald miller's uh building a
story brand uh has done an excellent job
in terms of making your marketing clear
and straightforward in terms of you know
helping drive more business to your
company and uh he has one i'm going
through now called business made simple
it's a 60-day exercise and just learning
how to get your business off the ground
and yeah so
a range of things there's also some
fiction in there uh celeste own wrote uh
two really good books uh everything i
never told you and little fires
everywhere that resonated with me
because they center around like asian
families and the shame culture that you
know that we all get uh you know kind of
run through as we grow up um yeah
there's just so many out there but yeah
if you had to start somewhere uh those
are some of my bread and butter books
and then also some of the more recent
ones that i'm cleaning useful
information from
nice nice yeah oh man there's so many
good books out there i've been um
my my roommate suggested a while back a
few months back he handed me one of his
books and it was a
this is like the way of the warrior or
or something like that but basically he
was handing it to me with uh kind of
like a suggestion to get out of my head
because i read all these you know uh
philosophy books or meditation books or
um uh you know the autobahn
autobiography of a yogi i'm reading all
these like self-help motivational books
and that's what i love doing um it helps
me helps me in in any of this sort of
world you know i feel like the the gems
that i'm able to to gain from those
books and repeat in my own words is
helpful to people um
but uh so taking his advice i didn't
read the book that he handed me because
i was uh he's like do something less
non-fiction do something that's just
enjoyable where you're just kind of
reading a book where there's not a goal
where you're just enjoying it
so i i refuted the book that he handed
me and then a couple months later i did
listen to what he said though i did
agree i was like okay i need to
i need to just enjoy reading so um i got
a i got a ready player two um
was it earnest klein
i got that on audible audible and just
finished that a couple days ago so
that was a good one so another um
fiction book that's that's worth reading
ready player two awesome
yeah yeah um
so in in the world of
let's see let's glance on my notes what
do we cover we covered a lot of good
stuff already terry
um
[Music]
the the internal conversation let's dip
our toes into that the internal
conversation between um
because that's kind of what we're all
experiencing right you know we have
these what does it look like when you're
talking to this person how does it look
like if you're watching the conversation
on the outside what about our internal
dialogue as we're having not only
conflict but um you know if we're coming
up in areas maybe it's not even in the
workplace where we're people pleasing
where we can bring awareness to these
things where we're noticing that they're
happening
what's this an internal dialogue look
like and how can we kind of prod it and
poke it towards the the correct powerful
uh areas yeah i mean that's uh that's a
fun one for sure uh so the example i
usually like to share
is that
in growing up right the opinions of
people you care about or respect or you
know you hold in highest team like your
parents right uh usually you transfer
that to yourself
um you know and so one example i shared
in another podcast was talking about how
um you know my parents had an
interesting long game and they told me
later when i grew up they said hey you
know we withheld a lot of praise because
we were afraid that if we gave you too
much like encouragement or you know good
job son like you wouldn't work as hard
and
one of the things i remember my dad
telling me is uh during one saturday
morning math session right everyone else
is watching cartoons but i have to do
sat prep books right um there was a
concept i was struggling with at some
point and so he said you know jerry give
let me give you a japanese lesson really
quick
ted
and so he's basically taught me japanese
to tell me that my head was made of
concrete
and
even funnier is that i could totally
hear my paternal grandpa his dad doing
that to him right because my my grandpa
grew up in taiwan during world war ii
and so they had to learn german and
japanese as part of axis domination
right and so this is what gets passed
down to me is that maybe if we tell him
he's stupid he'll work hard enough so we
don't have to tell him he's stupid
anymore
guess what i'm telling myself after i go
through this right oh i'm stupid i'm
just not worth it i don't know
right and then that transfers to other
areas of my life right you know a date
goes bad or it doesn't quite go it's
just like oh god so indebtable blah blah
blah right and so now even on the
outside when i i can do enough hard work
to you know finish the pharmacy school
degree get licensed get it present
myself well to get a job but i'm just
hating myself inside right
and
you know
for the longest time i didn't want to
tell people that i struggled with
insecurity i didn't want to admit that
this was a problem because it just felt
like such a stigma
and so it wasn't until even recently
um where i i
i would i remember when i moved to
houston and i mentioned that i started
with insecurity to a friend that had
recently gotten to know and she's like
oh yeah i struggled with that too and i
just said oh my gosh you know i can't
believe that
and that you know that was comforting
but you know it was a long way to go
right it's one thing to acknowledge the
problem in front of you in other to
actually try to you know develop a plan
or to uh you know tell your approach to
actually deal with these like uh you
know limiting beliefs or as jim quick
says you know i automatic negative
thoughts right uh so
uh the first kind of to go back to the
practical plan right you know
what are you doing to generate awareness
is the first question i like to ask
people uh because that's usually the
first thing that people overlook they're
so distraction prone oh hey i got
another like on instagram i could do all
this other stuff and they don't want to
deal with like the bigger problems in
front of them and i try not to make fun
of you know technicians i work with in
past but they're always on their phones
and it's just kind of like okay on one
hand i'm already annoyed that you're
probably not working on what you need to
be number two
even worse you're not even being
productive with that time like if you're
on an ebook i gave you you know great
maybe i might roll my eyes but at least
you know even if you're not doing the
immediate task at hand at least you know
you're still developing yourself but
yeah to generate that awareness to say
you know journal or something right just
ask yourself why am i thinking what am i
thinking you know how did this get here
why am i telling myself this and then to
say you know is this helpful is this
accurate you know what
why do i think it's accurate i've been
caught so many times jacob i don't know
about you uh you know a girl doesn't
return my texts in like the next five
minutes and i've already assumed that
she's blown me off right it's just you
know just the stories i guess i'm
uninteresting
okay i guess she's not that excited
about me
um
and so yeah so to really first catalog
your thoughts
and then but to also ask yourself okay
you know if do i like what i'm seeing or
do i like what i'm observing okay what
do i want to do about this how do i
change this how do i want to respond to
this um you know do i need help right if
it is a clinical issue then yeah by all
means there's no shame in that uh one of
the earliest podcasts i did was with the
clinton clinical psychologist out on the
west coast
he was highlighting the mental health
journeys of all these asian you know
celebrities and it is
honestly ridiculous to hear some of the
things that they've been through and
what they tell themselves you know you
hear extreme bouts of depression with
like mark with joe and all those other
things like william hung has had two
divorces and he's like wait i thought
they achieved the success and then it
turns out nope they they have life
stress just like everybody else
um
and so yeah all that to say right yeah
first ask yourself do i like what's on
my mind yes or no if i do how do i build
on it you know what do i what where do i
take that next step how do i take it to
the next level or if i don't like it hey
it's okay you know glad i found out and
what help do i need who can help me kind
of maybe change my narrative a little
bit so that i'm actually on a more
productive path
right right
yeah wow that's incredibly valuable
right there jerry um i was thinking
about the uh when you were mentioning
the technicians being on their phones it
just makes me think about so i'm i'm a
millennial and so i definitely you know
earl early high school i was you know we
had myspace we had we had the the
internet you know but i was still at the
beginning when we were using dial up and
we kind of transitioned into where you
can actually someone could be on the
phone in in your house
while you're while you're also on the
computer it was this cool thing yeah no
i missed that yeah just fun stories yeah
so uh i mean we have this this big very
very different world very very changing
world you know as i get older i realized
so so in high school and then the few
years after high school i was very much
addicted to my phone i was always on
social media i didn't realize how often
i was i was not being present how often
i was i mean i would get to the point
where as people are talking to me i'm
like oh yeah i'm listening and then
suddenly i'm start scrolling through
instagram as i'm in a conversation and i
didn't realize how disconnected that was
making me feel um i didn't realize
the amount of times where if i was in an
uncomfortable situation i would just
pull out my phone um you know like the
the simple example of waiting for an
elevator and there's people around you
and you know maybe you don't want to
have conversation that's okay but even
just just sitting there and existing
just being like that was so difficult i
i pull out my phone and so you know and
i think this adds to a lot of our a lot
of our insecurities um
and in it
i don't know it just it's it's difficult
to solve a lot of our conflicts in so
many ways when we're so distracted by
all the pretty colors on our on our
phone so do you have do you have any
observations of kind of our our our
modern age with these with these phones
and don't get me wrong i love all the
things we're able to do it's amazing
it's literally a magic miracle in a box
like it's just this magic box in our
pocket that does whatever we want it to
do i'm so grateful for it but i do also
recognize and i'd like to point out the
ways and bring to our awareness that um
you know it how it doesn't help us to
consistently be on our phone and
consistently be pulling it out and
distracting ourselves and how much it
makes us not able to to sprint for long
periods of time um
when it comes to work so in the area of
of conflict resolution
how does how do our phones negatively
affect us
yeah
um
so i'll quote another um
book that i like and i and i'll i'll
cite what the office specifically says
about phones in that whole process or
smartphones anyway so eric barker is
barking up the wrong tree
everything we know about success is
mostly wrong easily one of the best and
like most encompassing books on defining
your success that anyone should read
just to ask yourself what am i really
wanting out of life uh but there is a
specific chapter he talks about a comic
book reference with like venom and how
it overtakes the host and everything
also the stuff for those of you who are
marvel fans great for those of you
aren't just look up the quick wiki
article and get up to speed on this um
and they compare this to a smartphone
where it says hey i love
you know
i love the power that this
device has and i also hate the power
that it can have over me
right and it's it's like you know
stephen covey called it so many years
ago right he said technology is a
wonderful servant but a terrible master
and that's true for money my money is a
right um and all that to say right yeah
like i remember when i first finally
decided to upgrade to a smartphone after
you know i realized that some of the
benefits i needed were not coming from
my basic phone not what everyone kept
making fun of
and i didn't know that the default
settings were to notify me every time i
got an email so like every five seconds
ding oh hey let me go check oh it's spam
okay out of the way
ding oh let me go check oh no nor spam
and i'd say this is worse than ever so
let me just turn off these distractions
now let me turn off these notifications
and i've been much more cognizant of
this it took me a while for me to
finally kind of
game my environment so that i would not
be on my smartphone late at night you
know doing duolingo lessons or anything
else that was moderately productive but
still you know i was losing sleep that i
you know sleep is much more important
than language learning at midnight right
um and so
to your point with conflict resolution
if you are not entirely present it will
never go well
right if people feel like you aren't
actually listening to them
good luck
right it's i remember i you know to your
point i remember when i was sitting at
dinner with a friend that hadn't seen in
a while and you know i had just gotten
the phone that would allow me to text
this was before i actually had a
smartphone where i said like the slider
and it was so cool but i remember
you know i was waiting on another friend
to contact me afterwards in order to go
to a convention i was in town with and
so i'm with this other friend who wasn't
part of that whole thing but you know
we're talking and you know and then i
get a ding on my phone and then you know
so i kind of i start to answer it and as
i'm starting to answer it i see him
slough off and also begin to answer
because he needed to you know text back
his wife and all of a sudden boom we
were in the same we were sitting at the
same table but we were more disconnected
than ever right and you know same thing
happens here
i put my phone in my backpack and i zip
it up just to be sure i don't touch it
at work any more than i have to um you
know or if i'm uh if i have to focus on
a project like you know recording a
podcast or something like that i make
sure my phone is like downstairs away
where i can't even
like get anywhere and i'll be happy to
admit it's right here next to me but i'm
doing my best just to make sure that
even if something happens i'm not
touching it because like how terrible
would that be oh yeah jacob great
question let me hang on a second no no
no no no no no no right yeah i'm sitting
there that would be that would be
completely disrespectful and then i
wouldn't get any more gigs because
they're just like yeah jerry you know
he's an interesting guy but he's just
he's composting he's addicted to he was
on twitter a lot during our conversation
everyone needs to listen to this podcast
it's really i promise you i'm doing pr
um but yeah basically with conflict if
you do not know how to read the room if
you do not read the other person
correctly right it is in your best
interest and for not just yours but for
the relationship and for the long-term
game um to pay attention not only to
what's being said but it's how it's
being said and the body language and and
the tone and everything else so that you
know exactly how you need to respond in
a way that shows that you care for them
you respect them
even if you disagree with them hey look
there's something bigger that we need to
shoot for so let's talk about how to do
that
yeah yeah because i think
you know you know
we can hear about body language in
itself and we kind of separate it from
it's interesting to learn about body
language in the psychology world because
you're like oh okay so if they're
standing like this and if they're doing
this they're reciprocating and blah blah
but really if you look at it
all of that yes plus um you know a more
holistic uh uh uh observation of of
someone actually listening you know i
think that
we
we when you're not fully tentative you
don't realize how much you're missing
you don't realize how much um
i i don't know i i think that life can
be a lot richer when you're when you're
really listening you know it's is
tempting as it is to pull out our little
pocket mosquito you know and it's
buzzing
but yeah i think i stole that from
russell brand actually i think i think
he said it before
but yeah it's it's uh it's it's this
this gift and a curse this thing um our
phones you know it's this wonderful
wonderful thing but it uh i think it
actually is is pretty important i
noticed how much more you know like i've
seen with body language where
we really are
a lot of times we were communicating
with more than just our words right it's
it's a lot of times
i'm not listening to exactly what you're
saying i'm trying to understand what do
you mean you know you're trying to poke
this epiphany um of of understanding
within me and it's not always the exact
words you know we get we get kind of
hung up on the words but
it really is when you when you're
listening when when you're tentative it
communicates this this much bigger um
this this much bigger thing to the
person i think about um
when i was younger i used to work um so
it's like 16 to 19 i worked in the mall
i had a few different jobs in the mall
customer service and
at that time it was certainly
it was
it was an environment of we all had
phones
but it wasn't yet okay to where we've
all kind of accepted we're all just
going to have them and as long as you
use it appropriately you just pull it
put it back in your pocket and get back
to the customer
it was very much a hey man you need to
leave your phone in the back room like
there's no reason why you need to have
your phone that's just kind of how it
was back then
and then now i i'll go to stores and
maybe it's because i learned this other
way um i'll go to stores and i'll see a
lot of young people they don't greet me
when i walk into the clothing store and
they're they're on their phone i'm kind
of looking around and i'm you know
there's maybe there's something up high
and i'm kind of like giving the side eye
like hey can you come come glance over
or whatever and they're they're texting
behind the counter or whatever um and so
and so
and i'm not trying to say this as like
some old man who's like hey back in my
day we had to keep our phones in the
back room you know but but there really
is you know
there's so much more just by me glancing
over at a clothing store
it really communicates so much to me to
have the other person meet my gays and
say what's up do you need help i'm here
for you i got you you know in in it it
improves it improves their social skills
you know the the skills that they're
going to have in the years to come like
a lot of my um i'm an introverted dude
but a lot of my external um sharpened
abilities came from working at clothing
stores being in customer service kind of
having to force myself to get out of my
comfort zone you know and uh i i think
maybe what i'm trying to say is just
just a reminder that the cell phone is
is is a comfort zone in in a lot of ways
and i think that um you know rounding it
back to conflict resolution a lot of
times we might be missing what each
other are really saying we might be
misunderstanding one another because
we're not fully present you know if the
phone's pulling you out of that maybe
maybe take a second look or turn off
notifications you know that that's a big
one that you said um turning off
notifications i did that i have a couple
things i have notifications on but for
the most part um i have notifications
off on you know social media like the
fun stuff that i don't really need to
respond to right now you know
yeah yeah um well jerry we are getting
up here for uh
up here in time i do have one more
question for you but before just so just
so we don't forget i want to make sure
we get um can we send the listeners to
like what's your website what are you
working on what are your socials let's
make sure we we get them sent your way
if they want to learn learn more about
your world absolutely thank you yeah the
website is www.adaptingleaders.com
and uh you can find me on linkedin
that's the one social channel i've been
focusing on for right now so yeah feel
free to you know find me on there uh if
you go to my website uh there are plenty
of buttons there you can hit to just get
a free 30-minute call just you know no
strings attached just tell me what
you're working on right tell me your
story
tell me you know how i can possibly be a
resource for you and whether you choose
to hire me formally as a coach or not or
you know help you know get me you know
if you want to hire me for a group
workshop say hey you know we've got some
major conflict dynamics at our
organization we think you know your
perspective uh would be would be helpful
to us win the day sure um but
for those of you who say hey you know my
budget's a little tight and i just need
to bootstrap it for right now my blog is
free uh and if you want to ask me
directly i'll you know you replay this
podcast and say hey jerry mentioned five
books that i should just start reading
right now yes get those out of used
books
use book website start reading hey you
know
come back and tell me hey those books
are really helpful you know i landed a
multi-million dollar deal so thank you
for your help you know whatever whatever
it leads to uh you know i've i've
learned you know as much as i you know
need enough cash flow to keep my my
doors open uh the biggest priority is
still helping people so um whether you
say hey you know i didn't hire him but
he was still very generous i hope people
still say that hey you know what tell me
but tell me why you didn't hire me tell
me why you picked someone over me so i
know how to improve my services so yeah
adaptingleaders.com and yeah uh just
find me there yes yes i love that
everybody check that out jerry's
stealing one more thing from your
website is the uh what could j food do
for you i love that
or is it foo or is it for you how do i
throw it you got it right okay
it actually made me giggle uh when i
when i glanced at that and saw that um
yeah so that was like reading through
everything
yeah right right um and i also will um
include uh
i'm sure certain i'll remember right um
i will also include that in the
description so we'll have a a clickable
link down there as well with all jerry's
info um okay so our last question i like
to send it off um sometimes i mix it up
but i've been kind of floating with this
one for quite a while yeah um
jerry what does the world need more of
right now
[Laughter]
i can i can just feel the bait just be
being like say love say well um
i think the world needs more
humility
i was i'll be happy to pull back the
curtain and say i think the world needs
more curiosity it's like no i think the
world needs more humility you can say
empathy but of all the good answers i
think the best one is humility because
humility leads to curiosity when you
know hey i don't know everything i don't
know what i don't know let me go but i
want to find out and you know when
humility you know how i approach
relationships or leadership i think uh
humility is uh what the world needs more
of right so this way we're not
grandstanding we're not you know we're
not puffing up our chest we're not
trying to say how great we are we're
saying how can i make the people around
me great and i think again it just comes
back to good leadership how do i make
the people around me great
man i love that so much that's so
perfect
that's so great okay jerry man i
appreciate you thank you so much for
your time um this was a great
conversation thank you for all the book
recommendations too i'm really pumped i
feel like i'm going to go back through
and write all these down and probably
add them to my list of of
eventual reads for sure and then also uh
thank you as a recovering people pleaser
uh i'm always working on these things so
it was really cool to get to dive into
your mind and uh and get some firsthand
advice from you man really thank you so
much again happy to help jacob please
please uh continue the dialogue even
after the podcast is over yeah
definitely man we'll have to stay in
touch um so yeah listeners take care of
yourself love yourself drink some water
stretch you know the deal get present
stretch your eyes out stretch your whole
body breathe from your diaphragm get
present be here
don't be distracted by your phone and
check out jerry's website
jerry thanks again man uh yeah we'll be
in touch we'll have to send some emails
back and forth after this all right all
right thanks man have a great day guys
yeah you too take care
into the junkyard love podcast
[Music]
at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age do we learn have better
conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
you